<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sff on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.json.blog/tags/sff/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sff on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://www.json.blog/tags/sff/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My confrontation with the mainstream</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2017/02/my-confrontation-with-the-mainstream</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 13:02:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2017/02/my-confrontation-with-the-mainstream</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can check my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/5380958-jason&#34;&gt;Goodreads profile&lt;/a&gt;. I love science fiction and fantasy. And I know in 2017 and everyone has already observed the dominance of &amp;ldquo;geek culture&amp;rdquo;, with the dominance of Disney properties from Marvel and now Star Wars. Hell, &lt;a href=&#34;http://io9.gizmodo.com/suicide-squad-is-now-an-oscar-winning-movie-1792769922&#34;&gt;Suicide Squad won a goddamn Oscar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style= &#34;float:right;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href = &#34;#powell_best_selling&#34;&gt;   
      &lt;figure&gt;
          &lt;img src = &#34;/img/powell_best_selling.jpg&#34; height = &#34;800&#34;&gt;
          &lt;figcaption&gt; Powell&#39;s Best Selling Fiction, 2017-02-26&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;#_&#34; class=&#34;lightbox&#34; id = &#34;powell_best_selling&#34;&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
          &lt;img src = &#34;/img/powell_best_selling.jpg&#34;&gt;
          &lt;figcaption&gt;Powell&#39;s Best Selling Fiction, 2017-02-26&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I never felt like SFF was all that mainstream. SyFy might have made (and renewed) a TV series based on &lt;em&gt;The Magicians&lt;/em&gt;, but I still feel like the disaffected entitled shit that held onto his love of genre fiction too long when I crawl into bed and hide in speculative fiction (thank you Quentin, for so completely capturing what a shit I was at 14).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I was confronted with the reality of SFF going mainstream at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.powells.com&#34;&gt;Powell&amp;rsquo;s City of Books&lt;/a&gt;. I was fully unprepared to see the contents of their Best Selling Fiction shelf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By my count, at least 16 of the top 42 are SFF. &lt;em&gt;The Name of the Wind&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Left Hand of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Fifth Season&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;2312&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Uprooted&lt;/em&gt; are some of the best books I&amp;rsquo;ve ready in the last four or five years. To think of these books as best sellers when they don&amp;rsquo;t have a TV show coming out (like &lt;em&gt;American Gods&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Handmaid&amp;rsquo;s Tale&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Man in the High Castle&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;The Magicians&lt;/em&gt;) and aren&amp;rsquo;t assigned in high school classrooms (&lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse-Five&lt;/em&gt;) is just shocking. In my mind, these aren&amp;rsquo;t best sellers, they&amp;rsquo;re tiny nods between myself and other quiet bookshoppers that we are kin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sad though. I am thrilled. I want to live in a world where I can just assume acquaintances are reading &lt;em&gt;The Fifth Season&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Uprooted&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>