<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Novblog Meta on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.json.blog/tags/novblog-meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Novblog Meta on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://www.json.blog/tags/novblog-meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>NaNo(Blo)WriMo</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/nanoblowrimo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/nanoblowrimo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;November marks the start of National Novel Writing Month (NaNoWriMo). The quick version is folks band together and support each other to write 50,000 words in November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to write a novel one day. I am not sure I could do it well, but I am pretty sure I could hit 50,000-80,000 words if I dedicated time to tell a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have a story to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this year, I have decided to not feel guilty about skipping out on another NaNoWriMo (&lt;em&gt;always the reader, never the author&lt;/em&gt;), and instead I am modifying it to meet my needs. With no story to tell and no experience tackling a single project the size of a novel, I am going to tackle a smaller problem&amp;ndash; this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of 50,000 words in 30 days, I am going to try and write 1000 words a day for the next four weeks. I will not hold myself to a topic. I will not even hold myself to non-fiction. I will not hold myself to a number of posts or the size of the posts I write. I will not even hold myself to true daily count, instead reviewing where I stand at the end of each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hoping that the practice of simply writing will grease my knuckles and start the avalanche that leads to writing more. A small confession&amp;ndash; I write two or three blog posts every week that never leave my drafts. I find myself unable to hit publish because the ideas tend to be far larger or far smaller than I anticipate when I set out to write and share my frustrations. I also get nervous, particularly when writing about things I do professionally, about not writing the perfect post that&amp;rsquo;s clear, heavily researched, and expresses my views definitively and completely. This month, I say goodbye to that anxiety and start simply hitting publish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will leave you with several warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things might get topically wacky. I might suddenly become a food blogger, or write about more personal issues, or write a short story and suddenly whiplash to talking about programming, education policy, or the upcoming election. If high volume, random topics aren&amp;rsquo;t your thing, you should probably unsubscribe from my RSS feed and check back in a month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I might write terrible arguments that are poorly supported and don&amp;rsquo;t reflect my views. This month, I will not accept my most common excuses for not publishing, which boil down to fear people will hold me to the views I express in my first-draft thinking. I am going to make mistakes this month in public and print the dialog I am having with myself. The voices I allow room to speak as I struggle with values, beliefs, and opinions may be shock and offend. This month, this blog is my internal dialog. Please read it as a struggle, however definitive the tone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am often disappointed that the only things I publish are smaller ideas written hastily with poor editing. Again, this month I embrace the reality that almost everything I write that ends up published is the result of 20 minutes of furious typing with no looking back, rather than trying to be a strong writer with a strong view point and strong support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that the end of this month I will have written at least a couple of pieces I feel proud of, and hopefully, I will have a little less fear of hitting publish in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
