<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bruno Education Grading Grading Policy Twie on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/bruno-education-grading-grading-policy-twie.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bruno Education Grading Grading Policy Twie on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/bruno-education-grading-grading-policy-twie.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Grading</title>
      <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/2012/09/thoughts-on-grading</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jsonbecker.com/2012/09/thoughts-on-grading</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/MrPABruno&#34;&gt;Bruno&lt;/a&gt; is a skeptic on &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholasticadministrator.typepad.com/thisweekineducation/2012/09/bruno-is-standards-based-grading-a-good-idea.html&#34;&gt;standards-based grading&lt;/a&gt;. He seems to think
that &amp;ldquo;mastery of content&amp;rdquo; is too abstract for students to work toward
and rightly cites evidence that motivation and changed behavior are
tightly linked to a sense of efficacy, which in turn is tightly linked
to feeling as though you know precisely what to do to get to a
particular outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But isn&amp;rsquo;t mastery of content essentially, &amp;ldquo;Do well on your assignments
and tests&amp;rdquo;? And while a massive, standards-based report card may be hard
for a parent to read, is it any more confusing than seeing awful results
on standardized tests and a student who clearly doesn&amp;rsquo;t read on
grade-level receive good grades because of participation, attendance,
and behavior? As a parent, how do you know to intercede on your child&amp;rsquo;s
behalf when you see a &amp;ldquo;B&amp;rdquo; which actually represents a C- on content
knowledge and skills and an A+ for effort, behavior, and completion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I am against including behavior, attendance, and effort as a
part of the same grade as academics. I think there needs to be a clear
place to present evidence of academic ability and growth independent of
behavioral growth. Both are important, and while linked, are certainly
not moving in lockstep for the typical child. Accurate information in
both domains is far better than falsely presenting a singular, mixed-up
&amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; about a child&amp;rsquo;s success in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the same reason I am not a fan of school report cards with a single
letter grade rating, I am not for just a single letter grade for
students. Ultimately, they both represent poor combinations of data that
obscure more than they reveal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing report cards or &amp;ldquo;grading&amp;rdquo; systems, both for program
evaluation and for students, always conjures one of the few concepts I
recall from linear algebra. It seems to me that any good grading system
should provide a basis, that is, a minimal set of linearly independent
vectors which, via linear combination, can describe an entire vector
space. Remove the jargon and you&amp;rsquo;re left with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measure the least amount of unrelated things possible that, taken
together, describe all there is to know about what you are measuring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single grade that combines all the effort, behavior, attendance, and
various unrelated academic standards I might get an overall description
that says &amp;ldquo;round&amp;rdquo;. But by separating out the data at some other level,
the picture might describe a golf ball and its dimples, a baseball and
its stitches, or a soccer ball with its hexagon-pentagon pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we need to find a way to let people know what kind of ball they
have.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>