<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Core Connector Department Of Planning And Development Downcity Providence Ri Streetcar Urban Development Westminster Street on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.json.blog/tags/core-connector-department-of-planning-and-development-downcity-providence-ri-streetcar-urban-development-westminster-street/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Core Connector Department Of Planning And Development Downcity Providence Ri Streetcar Urban Development Westminster Street on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://www.json.blog/tags/core-connector-department-of-planning-and-development-downcity-providence-ri-streetcar-urban-development-westminster-street/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why isn&#39;t the Core Connector using Westminster with full RoW?</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2011/11/why-isnt-the-core-connector-using-westminster-with-full-row</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2011/11/why-isnt-the-core-connector-using-westminster-with-full-row</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love that Providence is pursuing a streetcar. There are really just
two things I don&amp;rsquo;t understand about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://providencecoreconnector.com/&#34;&gt;Core Connector&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s proposal.
I&amp;rsquo;m going to tackle one in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the entire streetcar route shared with general traffic with no
dedicated right-of-way? Truthfully, this isn&amp;rsquo;t a massive issue except in
the core part of Downcity where there is substantial traffic during rush
hours along the street car route. But this makes the plan even more
perplexing because it&amp;rsquo;s precisely this portion of the route where an
obvious solution for dedicated light rail ROW exists- Westminster
Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.json.blog/img/Route-November-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Quick and dirty Core Connector modification&#34; title=&#34;CoreConnectorRouteModified&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red route above represents the proposed streetcar line. The green
line represents Westminster Street, a narrow, single lane, one-way
street that cuts through Downcity and in front of &lt;a href=&#34;http://suraprovidence.com/&#34;&gt;restaurants&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.queenofheartsandmodernlove.com/&#34;&gt;boutique&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shopwarf.com&#34;&gt;shopping&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uri.edu/prov/&#34;&gt;URI&lt;/a&gt;, etc. It brings the streetcar line
slightly closer to Johnson and Wales and slightly further from the
Dunkin Donuts Arena and Rhode Island Convention Center. While there is
real automobile traffic, this is almost entirely for two reasons. First,
Westminster has substantial on-street metered parking. Second,
Westminster is the East-&amp;gt;West one-way to counter Weybosset&amp;rsquo;s West-East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the two major Downcity planning projects underway are
removing the stress that leads to both of these uses. The Downtown
Circulator project is nearly complete, converting Empire and Weybosset
to two-way streets. Automobile traffic will almost certainly take the
wider and faster Washington and Weybosset Streets, adjacent to
Westminster, unless the goal is to find on the street parking. The
second project is the Core Connector itself, which provides more options
to get into Downcity without a car, hopefully reducing the need for
parking. There are also substantial parking capacity that&amp;rsquo;s
underutilized in the many surface lots and parking garages in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/4256071978_aaf18cb143_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A great shot from Flickr of Westminster at night&#34; title=&#34;Westminster at Night&#34; /&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:sourceone&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:sourceone&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, there is really no need for Westminster to have
street traffic. A dedicated ROW will increase the speed and
predictability of the streetcar. Additional pedestrian space along
Westminster could quickly be used by the cafes and restaurants and
street vendors that already are in the area. The only reason I could
come up with for not using Westminster as a dedicated right-of-way for
the streetcar is the need for a turn in or around Kennedy Plaza. There
are so many options for moving between Washington and Westminster that I
just can&amp;rsquo;t buy this as an insurmountable challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was unable to make it to the three recent public meetings about the
proposed route. If I were there, this would certainly be my first
question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:sourceone&#34;&gt;Sourced from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/ranjith-pix/&#34;&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/ranjith-pix/&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:sourceone&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>