<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dana Goldstein Diane Ravitch Edreform Education Education Policy Education Reform History Kevin Carey Mike Petrilli Tnr on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>/tags/dana-goldstein-diane-ravitch-edreform-education-education-policy-education-reform-history-kevin-carey-mike-petrilli-tnr/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dana Goldstein Diane Ravitch Edreform Education Education Policy Education Reform History Kevin Carey Mike Petrilli Tnr on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/dana-goldstein-diane-ravitch-edreform-education-education-policy-education-reform-history-kevin-carey-mike-petrilli-tnr/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Diane Ravitch, rebuttals.</title>
      <link>/2011/12/diane-ravitch-rebuttals./</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/diane-ravitch-rebuttals./</guid>
      <description>So I wrote a harsh post after reading a harsh article by Kevin Carey in The New Republic about Diane Ravitch. I still standby what I said. Namely, I&amp;rsquo;m very cautious about trusting Ravitch as a reliable narrator of history because I&amp;rsquo;m:
 unfamiliar with good historiography/methodology so it&amp;rsquo;s hard for me to judge the quality of her work simply from the product itself unaware of a rich discourse around education history in NYC and 20th century America in general that wrestles with, or even corroborates, Ravitch&amp;rsquo;s account certain that Ravitch&amp;rsquo;s more recent writings often mischaracterizes the power and meaning behind quantitative research and exhibits selection bias to fit a particular narrative generally distrustful of public academics, particularly when their writing is mainly outside of their primary discipline.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>