<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brown University Core Connector Department Of Planning And Development Jewelry District Knowledge District Providence Ri Streetcar Urban Development on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>/tags/brown-university-core-connector-department-of-planning-and-development-jewelry-district-knowledge-district-providence-ri-streetcar-urban-development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Brown University Core Connector Department Of Planning And Development Jewelry District Knowledge District Providence Ri Streetcar Urban Development on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/brown-university-core-connector-department-of-planning-and-development-jewelry-district-knowledge-district-providence-ri-streetcar-urban-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Downcity Residents Should Support the Core Connector and the Tax Makes Sense</title>
      <link>/2011/09/downcity-residents-should-support-the-core-connector-and-the-tax-makes-sense/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/downcity-residents-should-support-the-core-connector-and-the-tax-makes-sense/</guid>
      <description>As a resident of Downcity, I have been closely following the development of Providence&amp;rsquo;s Core Connector Study. The official route and payment options have now been proposed, as reported in the Projo.
Route I&amp;rsquo;m pleased to see that they prioritized frequent service through the main ridership areas (College Hill to Jewelry District and hospital) were prioritized over service to the train station. Jef Nickerson says it best over at GCPVD&amp;ndash; the train station is out-of-the-way and would dramatically increase rider time while having unclear implications for ridership, and the station is already very well served (and could easily be better served) by existing bus routes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>