<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Core Connector Department Of Planning And Development Downcity Jewelry District Knowledge District Providence Public Goods Rhode Island Ri Streetcar Tax Urban Development Westminster Street on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/core-connector-department-of-planning-and-development-downcity-jewelry-district-knowledge-district-providence-public-goods-rhode-island-ri-streetcar-tax-urban-development-westminster-street/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Core Connector Department Of Planning And Development Downcity Jewelry District Knowledge District Providence Public Goods Rhode Island Ri Streetcar Tax Urban Development Westminster Street on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/core-connector-department-of-planning-and-development-downcity-jewelry-district-knowledge-district-providence-public-goods-rhode-island-ri-streetcar-tax-urban-development-westminster-street/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Downtown Improvement District</title>
      <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/post/downtown-improvement-district/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jsonbecker.com/post/downtown-improvement-district/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/did5.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;DID taking care of Downcity planters&#34; title=&#34;DID Doing a Great Job&#34; /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer that some goods &lt;em&gt;should be&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_goods&#34;&gt;public&lt;/a&gt;. I do not believe that my tax dollars are about providing *direct* personal benefit. I like redistributed tax policy. But it is hard to be a Rhode Islander, surrounded by government institutions &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golocalprov.com/news/julia-steiny-woonsockets-nosedive-a-cautionary-tale/&#34;&gt;that&lt;/a&gt; are
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golocalprov.com/news/procap/&#34;&gt;failing&lt;/a&gt;, and feel good about the taxes I pay. Corruption and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.turnto10.com/news/2012/apr/06/former-uri-president-enters-sport-institute-scanda-ar-991425/&#34;&gt;cronyism&lt;/a&gt; is a daily reality of government business. Some agencies have &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ripec.org/pdfs/2009-AI-Study.pdf&#34;&gt;tremendous waste and inefficiency&lt;/a&gt;. Worse, many public institutions that are failing their mission and wasting money are actually woefully underfunded. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:underfunded&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:underfunded&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If more government institutions functioned like the Downtown Improvement District, there would be greater trust and support for government services.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the best money I spend each year is the approximately \$200-250 that I send to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://downtownprovidence.com/clean-safe/&#34;&gt;Downtown Improvement District&lt;/a&gt; (DID).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live within a special assessment district in Providence that levies an additional property tax to pay for the ladies and gentlemen in bright yellow jackets that are a constant presence in my neighborhood. For a small tax each year, my neighborhood gets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;substantial cleanup /sanitation services that removes the mountains of trash that can pile up during a busy night where &lt;a href=&#34;http://jwu.edu/providence/&#34;&gt;college students&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ppacri.org/&#34;&gt;theater&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trinityrep.com/&#34;&gt;goers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://graciesprovidence.com/&#34;&gt;restaurant patrons&lt;/a&gt;, nightclub patrons, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hotelprovidence.com/&#34;&gt;tourists&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.waterfire.org/&#34;&gt;Waterfire&lt;/a&gt; visitors all converge on Downcity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;excellent landscaping including planting and pruning trees, maintaining flowerbeds, hanging flower pots on light posts, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;responsive care of public property including removing safety hazards, e.g. removing the cement, waist-high barrier that had fallen on the sidewalk by my building that was a major safety hazard for pedestrians&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;easily identifiable public presence in addition to cops that increases the safety and security of busy city street&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;much, much more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem selfish, but honestly, this is the best government service I current receive. It is inexpensive. I am able to see a direct increase in my quality of life in Downcity. It clearly increases and protects my property investment. I get an annual budget that is fairly detailed
mailed annually that explains precisely what my dollars purchased and how they will be used in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the currently dormant[^0] &lt;a href=&#34;http://providencecoreconnector.com/&#34;&gt;Providence Core Connector&lt;/a&gt; announced they would seek to use a special assessment district to fund operation expenses, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/2011/09/26/downcity-residents-should-support-the-core-connector-and-the-tax-makes-sense/&#34;&gt;I was all for it&lt;/a&gt;. Sure, a
portion of my support came from the simple economics, but I would be lying if I did not admit that the wonderful relationship I have with the Downtown Improvement District was not a part of my consideration. The DID has provided an excellent model to Downcity residents demonstratingthe efficacy of using the greatest (but not sole) beneficiary of place-bound services as a revenue source. Does anyone really believe that Downtown would have doubled its residency from 2000-2010 &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:census&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:census&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; if the DID were not around?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.jasonpbecker.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/did5.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;DID taking care of Downcity planters&#34; title=&#34;DID Doing a Great Job&#34; /&gt;]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.providenceri.com/CityNews/newsletter2.php?id=290&#34;&gt;http://www.providenceri.com/CityNews/newsletter2.php?id=290&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:underfunded&#34;&gt;See Pawtucket and Woonsocket on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ride.ri.gov/Finance/funding/Uniform%20Chart%20of%20Accounts/2010/STATE/FY10%20Equalized%20Expenditures%20Report%20-%20Sorted.pdf&#34;&gt;this chart&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:underfunded&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:census&#34;&gt;US Census Bureau. Check out this &lt;a href=&#34;http://gis.providenceplanning.org/PVD_2010CensusViewer/&#34;&gt;great resource&lt;/a&gt; that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.providenceri.com/planning/&#34;&gt;Providence Planning Department&lt;/a&gt; put up
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:census&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>