<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Star Wars Force Awakens Trailers Sound on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/star-wars-force-awakens-trailers-sound.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Star Wars Force Awakens Trailers Sound on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/star-wars-force-awakens-trailers-sound.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power Of Sound</title>
      <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/2014/11/the-power-of-sound</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jsonbecker.com/2014/11/the-power-of-sound</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been said a thousand times before, but I feel the need to say it again. So much of what Star Wars got right was creating a fully realized, fascinating world. As much as stunning visual effects that have largely stood the test of time were a part of that story, it was how Star Wars &lt;em&gt;sounded&lt;/em&gt; that is most remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch that trailer. It has moments that &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; an awful lot like Star Wars&amp;ndash; vast dunes in the middle of the desert, the Millenium Falcon speeding along, flipping at odd angles emphasizing its unique flat structure. But it also has a lot of elemetns that are decidedly modern and not Star Wars like. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:shakes&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:shakes&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I think what&amp;rsquo;s most remarkable is I can close my eyes and just listen. Immediately I can &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; Star Wars. The sounds of Star Wars are not just iconic, they are deeply embedded in my psyche and embued with profound meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first had the opportunity to see Star Wars on the big screen it was during the release of the &amp;ldquo;Special Editions&amp;rdquo;. There is nothing like hearing Star Wars in a theater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:shakes&#34;&gt;Shakey-cam is the primary culprit.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:shakes&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>