<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.json.blog/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.json.blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing json.blog</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2016/12/introducing-jsonblog</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2016/12/introducing-jsonblog</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have written a lot on the internet. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a surprise, I&amp;rsquo;ve been here since the mid-90s. But the truth is, most of what I write on the internet doesn&amp;rsquo;t make me proud. It hasn&amp;rsquo;t made the world any better. It certainly hasn&amp;rsquo;t made me feel any better. Most of this terrible writing is easy to associated with me, because a long time ago, I chose to use my real name as my online identity. Using my real name was supposed to make sure that I would stand by what I said, but the truth is that I am not always my better self on internet forums, Facebook, Twitter, or other places I get to write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal blog is a bit different. The writing I&amp;rsquo;ve done over the years at my own domains has been&amp;hellip; less embarrassing. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to say that the quality of the writing is any better (it&amp;rsquo;s not); it&amp;rsquo;s just that the extra thought involved in opening up a text editor, writing something in Markdown, and taking the steps to post it has resulted in fewer emotional tirades. I do a much better job of deleting or never completing posts on my blog than I ever did writing somewhere someone else owned. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad the audience here is much smaller and harder to come by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My blog has always been a testing ground. It&amp;rsquo;s where I&amp;rsquo;ve learned how to use Wordpress, Pelican, and now Hugo. It&amp;rsquo;s been a place to think about templating, structure, CSS, shared hosting, Github pages, server management, nginx and the like. This is where I try different types of writing like link posts, lists, professional-ish informational posts, public versions of notes to myself, images, and more. This blog hasn&amp;rsquo;t had a topic or a format. I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced it ever will. For me, a self-hosted blog is meant to be a personal lab bench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope today I am starting what I consider to be the final version of this blog. I feel confident in the domain and name. I feel comfortable with Hugo and the flexiblility of my fully custom theme. I feel great about not having comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The look and content will change many times again, but I feel good that from here forward I&amp;rsquo;ll be using and evolving &lt;a href=&#34;http://json.blog&#34;&gt;json.blog&lt;/a&gt;. This is my home on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Songs in the Key of Allovue</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2016/07/songs-in-the-key-of-allovue</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2016/07/songs-in-the-key-of-allovue</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I entered high school, video games were beginning to lose their appeal. So I sold my four video game systems and all their games at a garage sale and that money, plus some Chanukkah money, bought me my first guitar and amp. I had just tried joined a band as a singer with a couple of guys I knew from school. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know anything about playing guitar. In fact, it took me a while to figure out what distortion was and why I my guitar didn&amp;rsquo;t sound like Kris Roe from The Ataris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, being in a band was rough. We had a lot of fun playing together, but just keeping time and making it all the way through a song was a slog. We had agreed I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t try playing guitar with the band until I had been playing at least three months, self-taught. But this was 2001 and I lived on Long Island and we were playing pop-punk, so it didn&amp;rsquo;t take too long to catch up. Soon I was writing music, actual original music. To this day, I don&amp;rsquo;t really enjoy playing other people&amp;rsquo;s music, because from the moment I picked up a guitar it was an instrument for creating new music with other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing music was a kind of awful torture I was addicted to. For years, I was absorbing how music sounded. I used to listen so intently that I memorized whole compositions. I wanted to hear every strike of a kick drum, every open string ringing out, every tapped bass note, and every quiet piano layered in deep below the mix. But now that I was writing music, I became become obsessed with its construction. All the nuances I worked hard to hear in music took on a whole new layer of depth as I tried unravel how the song was made. I never heard music the same way again. But my appreciation for the craft of songwriting far exceeded the meager results a few months of having a stratocaster glued to my hands could produce. I would meet and practice with just one of the other members of the band for hours long writing sessions where we would struggle to create something good enough to bring to the rest of the guys and flesh out into a full song. But eventually, within a couple of years, we wrote about 15 songs, at least six or seven of which I was pretty proud of. It was so difficult to write those first songs. It took so many hours at home alone, then working hard with one or two other guys to write new parts and determine a structure, and then eventually months of practice with four guys sweating in a basement practicing the same music over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted so badly to write my song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every band has one. Their song. The real one. The song that every musician who hears your album recognizes immediately as the song that trancends the talent of the individuals involved and is just plain better. It&amp;rsquo;s not the most complex song. It may not even be the most overtly emotional. It&amp;rsquo;s probably not your single. But it&amp;rsquo;s the song that stands out as a proud announcement to the people like me, the musicians who absorb every sound and experience the very structure of the music. Transcendent, to repeat myself, is really the best explanation for it. These are the songs that shook my soul, and I wanted to find mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never did write my song. I ended up quitting that first band after two and a half years and playing with a different set of guys for a bit over year chasing &amp;ldquo;my song&amp;rdquo;. I hoped a different writing experience with different musicians might help. Throughout college, I still played guitar all the time, but I never got comfortable writing without collaborators and I never found the right people to fulfill that role. Nowadays I pick up a guitar so rarely. I hear a phrase in a song I love and immediately know I can play it and sometimes get the urge to actually prove that to myself. Once a year, the foggy edges of a song appears in the distance, enticing me to chase it for a short while, and I record a small phrase to add to the library of forgotten riffs and lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still listen to music, though not as often and not really the same kinds anymore. And I still can&amp;rsquo;t listen the way I used to, the way it was before I picked up a guitar and tried singing into a microphone. That part of me is permanently broken in a way I expect only musicians can understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned something important about myself in my time as a musician. When I&amp;rsquo;m chasing something I truly love, I don&amp;rsquo;t feelsome great pleasure. Writing music was about throwing myself into an agonizing chase for the impossible. It was the euphoria of the small accomplishments&amp;ndash; a good song performed on stage in front of a crowd that actually responds to your creation, or cracking how to transition from a verse to a chorus&amp;ndash; that kept me going. And it was the imprint on my life, mind and soul, that brought me true joy from being a musician as time went on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on product at Allovue feels like writing music. I have never done something this hard, but I do know what it is like to experience a profound &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; so deeply. There are moments of real euphoria, like when a user describes their experience with Balance in a way so perfectly aligns with our vision that I triple check they are not a plant. And there are moments of agony, like almost every time I start to &amp;ldquo;listen&amp;rdquo; to our product and deconstruct it, and feel the weight of a decade&amp;rsquo;s worth of ideas on what our product needs to match the vision I have had since the first time Jess told me what she&amp;rsquo;s trying to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels like for the first time, I just might be writing my song. The real one. And I&amp;rsquo;m terrified I&amp;rsquo;m not good enough or strong enough or just plain enough to see it through.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on sequels</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2016/04/a-note-on-sequels</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2016/04/a-note-on-sequels</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I read a lot of science fiction and fantasy, genres filled with long running book series. Until the last couple of years, I mostly avoided any series that wasn&amp;rsquo;t already complete. First, I don&amp;rsquo;t like truly “epic” sci-fi fantasy. On-going series without an end in sight, or series that go beyond roughly 3,000 to 4,000 pages never end well for me&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I simply lose interest. Second, I worry that series won&amp;rsquo;t actually reach completion, either because the books are not successful enough or the author gets writer&amp;rsquo;s block&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or even just getting caught up in waiting way too long between books&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Third, I like to actually remember what happened, especially in the kind of complex stories I like to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some series do really well with sequels. I recently read through Kelly McCullough&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Fallen Blade&lt;/em&gt; series, and although it is complete and I did read the books in succession, they always made a clear attempt to reintroduce everything about the novel and the necessary bits of past events. In fact, McCullough was so good at this , it was almost obnoxious to read the series all in one go&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But other books seem to provide no help at all. And I am now deeply invested in several series that have not yet completed. Right now I&amp;rsquo;m finally reading &lt;em&gt;Poseidon&amp;rsquo;s Wake&lt;/em&gt;, the third and final novel in Alastair Reynolds&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Poseidon&amp;rsquo;s Children&lt;/em&gt; trilogy. Because it had been so long, I had forgotten critical parts of the earlier two novels that I enjoyed so much. Now, nearly 40% through the book and thoroughly engrossed, most of the key information has miraculously come back to me. But I found it difficult to get through the first 5% or so of the novel if for no other reason than I was trying to remember what was in *Blue Remembered Earth*and what was in Kim Stanley Robinson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;2312&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit, I am often impressed with my own ability to recall details of a story I read years earlier when encountering a sequel, because I seem to remember far more of it than expected.  But I wonder, what must the editing process on a sequel be like? How do authors and editors decide what can be assumed and what cannot?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;See &lt;em&gt;Wizard&amp;rsquo;s First Rule&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;A Song of Ice and Fire&lt;/em&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;See Patrick Rothfuss.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;I think I really learned this waiting for the conclusion of &lt;em&gt;His Dark Materials&lt;/em&gt;, which felt like it took a goddamn life time.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;I assume these books must be geared toward young adults and that this impacted the “hand holding” involved in moving from book to book. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if they&amp;rsquo;re considered YA fiction, but the writing certainly had that feel. Still, they were wonderfully fun quick reads. I read all six books from November 23rd through December 14th.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;A novel I did not enjoy nearly as much, but which seemed to have very similar themes and setting and which I read three months prior to &lt;em&gt;Blue Remembered Earth&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;On the Steel Breeze&lt;/em&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to Tumblr</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2015/07/returning-to-tumblr</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2015/07/returning-to-tumblr</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have had a &lt;a href=&#34;http://tumblr.jsonbecker.com&#34;&gt;Tumblr site&lt;/a&gt; for a long time but never knew what to do with it. What is Tumblr exactly? Is it a hosted blog? Is it a hosted blog for hipsters? Is it a social network? Why should I put content into Tumblr?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have this &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.jsonbecker.com&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;, but I barely use it. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a Facebook page, because I don&amp;rsquo;t trust Facebook and how it repeatedly changed and confused privacy settings and after college, I rarely found that Facebook was a net positive in my life. Recently I crossed &lt;em&gt;1000&lt;/em&gt; followers on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the sense of control offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.jsonbecker.com/2015/01/taking-control.html&#34;&gt;owning where I put content&lt;/a&gt;. But the barrier to posting a blog post has always felt high to me. A blog feels somewhat permanent. It&amp;rsquo;s something I want my current and future employers and friends to read it. It&amp;rsquo;s a record of ideas that felt worthy of memorializing. I have tried over and over again to lower this perceived barrier to blogging and failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I find the quick ability to favorite/like, retweet/re-broadcast, and respond on Twitter to be addicting. It is so easy to give feedback and join a conversation. As a result, I&amp;rsquo;ve probably written more, 140 characters at a time, on Twitter than I ever have on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, Twitter is an ephemeral medium. It is about instant conversation and access. What I dump into Twitter doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any lasting power, which is why it&amp;rsquo;s so easy to toss out thoughts. Twitter is my new &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat&#34;&gt;IRC&lt;/a&gt;, not a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microblogging&#34;&gt;microblog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing on Twitter in 140 characters often seems to attract the worst in people. It&amp;rsquo;s not just #gamergate, it&amp;rsquo;s me. My ideas are more sarcastic, more acerbic, and less well considered because Twitter feels like an off the cuff conversation among friends. But it&amp;rsquo;s not a conversation among friends. It&amp;rsquo;s not really even a conversation. It&amp;rsquo;s a bunch of people shouting at each other in the same room. Twitter is less a late night dorm room debate and more the floor of the New York Stock Exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to Tumblr, a service I think I finally understand. Tumblr is Twitter, but for people who take a breath before shouting. It has the same rich post types that Twitter has implemented through Cards. It has the same ability to magnify posts I find interesting through its reblogging feature. It also has the same ability to send a bit of encouragement and acknowledgement through its hearts. But Tumblr also doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the limitation of 140 characters, so I can spread my thoughts out just a bit further. And Tumblr does have a reply/conversation mechanism, but it&amp;rsquo;s just slightly “heavier” feeling than a Twitter reply so I&amp;rsquo;m less likely to just shoot off my mouth with the first thoughts that come to mind. Though Tumblr is a hosted service, it also has a fairly good API that can be used to export posts and the ability to use a custom URL. I could generate more post types on my Pelican blog, but a self-hosted blog lacks some of the social features that are just fun. And the truth is, do I really want to just put a link to a song I&amp;rsquo;m listening to right now on my blog? Is that kind of ephemera really worthy of a blog post? Maybe, but that&amp;rsquo;s not the kind of blog I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am going back to Tumblr. I have been experimenting for a couple of days and I really like having a place to dump a link or a funny picture. I don&amp;rsquo;t want Tumblr to host my blog, but I do want Tumblr to eat into some of my Twitter posting. I can easily syndicate Tumblr posts over to Twitter, so why not take a little more space and &lt;em&gt;breathe&lt;/em&gt; before deciding it is worth sharing something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;a href=&#34;http://tumblr.jsonbecker.com&#34;&gt;follow me on Tumblr&lt;/a&gt;. I think it&amp;rsquo;s going to be really fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted on both my &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.jsonbecker.com&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; and my &lt;a href=&#34;http://tumblr.jsonbecker.com&#34;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News on Assertions in R</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2015/07/news-on-assertions-in-r</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2015/07/news-on-assertions-in-r</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How many times have you written R functions that start with a bunch of code that looks like this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;my_funct &amp;lt;- function(dob, enddate = &amp;quot;2015-07-05&amp;quot;){
if (!inherits(dob, &amp;quot;Date&amp;quot;) | !inherits(enddate, &amp;quot;Date&amp;quot;)){
    stop(&amp;quot;Both dob and enddate must be Date class objects&amp;quot;)
  } 
...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because R was designed to be interactive, it is incredibly tolerant to bad user input. Functions are not &lt;em&gt;type safe&lt;/em&gt;, meaning function arguments do not have to conform to specified data types. But most of my R code is not run interactively. I have to trust my code to run on servers on schedules or on demand as a part of production systems. So I find myself frequently writing code like the above&amp;ndash; manually writing type checks for safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been some great action in the R community around &lt;em&gt;assertive programming&lt;/em&gt;, as you can see in the link. My favorite development, by far, are type-safe functions in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/smbache/ensurer&#34;&gt;ensurer package&lt;/a&gt;. The above function definition can now be written like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;my_funct &amp;lt;- function_(dob ~ Date, enddate ~ Date: as.Date(&amp;quot;2015-07-05&amp;quot;), {
  ...
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the type-checking is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the reuse of the formula notation &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; and the use of &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; to indicate default values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with packages like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hadley/testthat&#34;&gt;testthat&lt;/a&gt;, R is really growing up and modernizing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhode Island Disease</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2015/06/rhode-island-disease</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2015/06/rhode-island-disease</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When discussing policy in Rhode Island, I almost always encounter two bizarre arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhode Island is completely unique. Ideas from other places don&amp;rsquo;t adequately take into account our local context. What is working there either won&amp;rsquo;t work here or isn&amp;rsquo;t really comparable to our situation here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is happening nationally is directly applicable to Rhode Island. We can make broad sweeping statements about a set of policies, ideas, or institutions currently in play in Rhode Island without any knowledge of how things are going locally and how it&amp;rsquo;s different from other places. We can simply graft a broader national narrative onto Rhode Island regardless of whether it makes any sense with our facts on the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These seemingly in conflict points of view are often employed by the same actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is probably not unique to Rhode Island, but that won&amp;rsquo;t stop me from calling it &lt;strong&gt;Rhode Island Disease&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acceptable Terms</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2015/04/acceptable-terms</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2015/04/acceptable-terms</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gcpvd.org/2015/04/15/pawsox-providence-stadium-proposal/&#34;&gt;initial proposal&lt;/a&gt; has been made to the city of Providence and state of Rhode Island to keep the PawSox in Rhode Island and move them to a new stadium along the river in Providence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team is proposing that they privately finance all of the construction costs of the stadium while the land remains state (or city? I am not clear) owned. The state will lease the land underneath the stadium (the real value) with an option to buy for 30 years at $1 a year. The state will also pay $5,000,000 rent for the stadium itself annually for 30 years. The PawSox will then lease back the stadium at $1,000,000 per year. The net result will be the stadium is built and Rhode Island pays the PawSox owners $4,000,000 a year for 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-good&#34;&gt;The Good&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Privately financing the upfront cost of the stadium puts risks of construction delays and cost overruns on the PawSox. Already they are underestimating the cost of moving a gas line below the park grounds. Whatever the cost of construction, whatever the impact on the team of a late opening, the costs to the state are fixed. There is essentially no risk in this plan for taxpayers, defining risk as a technical term for uncertainty. We know what this deal means: $120,000,000 over 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest rate is pretty low. Basically, although the risk is privatized, we should view this stadium as the PawSox providing the state of Rhode Island a loan of $85,000,000 which we will pay back at a rate of approximate 1.15% &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:interest&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:interest&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Now just because the interest is low doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we should buy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stadium design is largely attractive, even if the incorporated lighthouse is drawing ire. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind it, but I do like the idea of replacing it with an Anchor has some Greater City Providence commenters have recommended. Overall, I think the design fits with the neighborhood. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to get caught up in pretty renderings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pedestrian bridge remains and is accessible. As someone who lives in Downcity, I am very much looking forward to this dramatic improvement to my personal transit. I think the bridge&amp;rsquo;s importance for transit is underrated, although admittedly we could make Point Street Bridge friendlier to pedestrians and bike riders instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brown University seems interested in hosting events, like football games, at the stadium. The plan also seems to give the state a lot of leeway in holding various events in the space when it&amp;rsquo;s not used for the baseball season. It could really be a great event space from mid-April until early November each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bad&#34;&gt;The Bad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the team&amp;rsquo;s own economic estimates only foresee $2,000,000 in increased tax revenues. Although they claim this estimate is conservative, I would take that with a huge grain of salt. You do not lead with a plan that straight up says the taxpayers will be out $60,000,000 over 30 years unless you don&amp;rsquo;t have a better foot to put forward. I am going to go ahead and assume this estimate is about right. It&amp;rsquo;s certainly in the ballpark. (Ugh.) But what that means is that Rhode Islanders should understand this is &lt;em&gt;not an investment&lt;/em&gt;. This is not like building transit infrastructure or tax stabilization agreements to spur private construction. This deal is more akin to building schools. We do not, in fact cannot, expect that the economic impact makes this project a net positive for revenues. With $12,000,000 expected in direct spending, the project could be net positive for GDP, but even then it is obvious this is not the best annual investment to grow the economy. It is easy to come up with a laundry list of projects that cost less than this that could create more economic activity and/or more revenue to the state and city. Therefore, the project should be viewed primarily on use value. Will Rhode Islanders get $4,000,000 a year in value from the pleasure of using (and seeing) this stadium and its surrounding grounds? In school construction, we expect the benefits to be short term job creation, long term impacts on student health and well-being, ability to learn, and our ability to attract quality teachers. But most of those benefits are diffuse and hard to capture. Ultimately, we mostly support school construction because of the use benefits the kids and teachers see each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time line is crazy. If they&amp;rsquo;re serious about a June decision, they&amp;rsquo;re nuts. We have a complicated budget process ongoing right now. We have a teacher contract in Providence to negotiate. We have a brand new I-195 Commission trying to make their mark and get cranes in the sky. There&amp;rsquo;s no way a negotiation in good faith can be completed in 60 days unless they agree to every counter. If this is a &amp;ldquo;final best offer&amp;rdquo;, essentially, due to time line, then it is disingenuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens in 30 years? We don&amp;rsquo;t have any guarantees of being whole in 30 years, and the same threats and challenges posed by the PawSox today will come up again in 30 years. Are we committed to a series of handouts until the team is of no monetary or cultural value?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other cities are likely going to come into play. The PawSox don&amp;rsquo;t have to negotiate a deal that&amp;rsquo;s fair for Rhode Island. They just have to negotiate to a deal that&amp;rsquo;s comparable to an offer they think someone else will make. Rhode Island&amp;rsquo;s position is weak, provided that anyone else is willing to make a deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-strange&#34;&gt;The Strange&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PawSox are asking for a 30-year property tax exemption. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot to think through here. First, there are at least two parcels that were meant to be tax generating that are a part of this plan&amp;ndash; the land Brown&amp;rsquo;s Continuing Education building currently sits on and the small develop-able parcel that was cut out from the park for a high value hotel or similar use. The stadium wants both of these parcels in addition to the park. I think City Council President Aponte is being a bit silly talking about being &amp;ldquo;made whole&amp;rdquo; over this deal, unless he&amp;rsquo;s talking about those two parcels. The park land was never going to generate city tax revenue and was actually going to cost the city money to maintain. Part of my openness to any proposal on this park land is my lack of confidence that the city will invest appropriately to maintain a world-class park space along the waterfront. There&amp;rsquo;s very little &amp;ldquo;whole&amp;rdquo; to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible that Providence will have to designate additional park space if the stadium is built. If that&amp;rsquo;s true and it&amp;rsquo;s coming off the tax roles than the PawSox absolutely should have to pay property taxes, period. There&amp;rsquo;s one possible exception I&amp;rsquo;ll address below&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also feel very strongly about having a single process for tax stabilization across all I-195 land that is not politically driven but instead a matter of administrative decision. Exceptions for a big project breaks the major benefit of a single tax stabilization agreement ruling all the I-195 land, which is our need to send a signal that all players are equal, all developers are welcome, and political cronyism is not the path required to build. While some of those $2,000,000 in tax benefits will accrue to Providence through increased surrounding land value, many costs associated with the stadium will as well. There are police details, road wear and tear, fire and emergency services, and more to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-counter&#34;&gt;My Counter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think this deal is dead, but I am not sure that the PawSox, city, or state would accept my counter. I have struggled with whether I should share what I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to happen versus what I think a deal that &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; happen looks like. I would be tempted to personally just let the PawSox walk. But if Rhode Island really wants them to stay, here&amp;rsquo;s a plausible counter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The PawSox receive the same tax stabilization agreement all other developers get from the city of Providence. Terms for a fair valuation of the property are agreed upon up front that are derived from some portion of an average of annual revenues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lease terms should be constructed such that the net cost (excluding the anticipated increase in tax receipts) is equal to the tax dollars owed to the city of Providence. Therefore, the state essentially pays for the $85,000,000 of principal and the city taxes. This could be through a PILOT, but I&amp;rsquo;d prefer that amount go to the PawSox and the PawSox transfer the dollars to the city. It&amp;rsquo;s just accounting, but I prefer the symbol of them paying property taxes. I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s a terrible precedent for the state to offer PILOT payments to cover a gap between the city TSA in I-195 with a developer&amp;rsquo;s ask, if the state sees there is substantial public interest in that investment, but still better to actually get developers used to writing a check to the city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the city has to make additional green space equivalent to the park we are losing, I foresee two options. First is the PawSox paying full load on whatever that land value is. The second is probably better, but harder to make happen. Brown should give up the Brown Stadium land to the city. They can make it into a park without reducing the foot print of taxable property in the city. If they did this, Brown should essentially get free use of the stadium with no fees (except police detail or similar that they would pay for their games on the East Side) in perpetuity. They should get first rights after the PawSox games themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stadium itself will be reverted to ownership by the Rhode Island Convention Center Authority if the option to buy the land is not exercised in 30 years. This way the whole stadium and its land are state owned, since the state paid for it. The possible exception would be if Brown has to give up its stadium to park land, in which case I might prefer some arrangement be made with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The PawSox ownership agrees to pay a large penalty to the state and the city if they move the team out of Rhode Island in the next 99 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PawSox maintenance staff will be responsible for maintaining the Riverwalk park, stadium grounds, and the green-way that has been proposed for the I-195 district. Possible we can expand this to something like the Downcity Improvement District (or perhaps just have them pay to expand the DID into the Knowledge District). This will help ensure this creates more permanent jobs and reduces costs to the city for maintaining its public spaces that contribute to the broader attractiveness of the stadium.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There should be a revenue share deal for any non-PawSox game events with the city and/or state for concession purchases and parking receipts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stadium should not be exempt from future TIF assessments for infrastructure in the area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure that I would pay even that much for the stadium, but this would be a far better deal overall. I can absolutely think of better ways to spend state dollars, but I also realize that the trade-off is not that simple. Rhode Island is not facing a windfall of $85,000,000 and trying to decide what to do with it. A stadium that keeps the PawSox in Rhode Island inspires emotion. The willingness to create these dollars for this purpose may be far higher than alternative uses. The correct counterfactual is not necessarily supporting 111 Westminster (a better plan for less). It is not necessarily better school buildings. It is not necessarily meaningful tax benefits for rooftop solar power. It is not lowering taxes, building a fund to provide seed capital to local startups, a streetcar, dedicated bus and/or bike lanes, or tax benefits to fill vacant properties and homes. The correct counterfactual could be nothing. It could be all of these things, but in much smaller measure. It is very hard to fully evaluate this proposal because we are not rational actors with a fixed budget line making marginal investment decisions. Ultimately, with big flashy projects like this, I lean toward evaluating them on their own merits. Typically, and I think this case is no exception, even evaluating a stadium plan on its own merits without considering alternative investments makes it clear these projects are bad deals. Yet cities and states make them over and over again. We would be wise to look at this gap in dollars and cents and our collective, repeated actions not as fits of insanity but instead as stark reminders of our inability to simply calculate the total benefits that all people receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my day job, I get to speak to early stage investors. There I learned an important tidbit&amp;ndash; a company can name whatever valuation they want if an investor can control the terms. That&amp;rsquo;s my feeling with the PawSox. The cash is important, it&amp;rsquo;s not nothing. But any potential plan should be judged by the terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s hoping Rhode Island isn&amp;rsquo;t willing to accept bad terms at a high cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:interest&#34;&gt;$A = P(1 + \frac{r}{n})^{nt}$ where $A = $120,000,000$, $P = $85,000,000$, $n = 1$, and $t = 30$. I&amp;rsquo;ll leave you to the algebra.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:interest&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A PostgreSQL Cheat Sheet for OSX and R</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2015/01/a-postgresql-cheat-sheet-for-osx-and-r</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2015/01/a-postgresql-cheat-sheet-for-osx-and-r</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I keep this on my desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;brew install postgresql
initdb /usr/local/var/postgres -E utf8
gem install lunchy
### Start postgres with lunchy
mkdir -p ~/Library/LaunchAgents
cp /usr/local/Cellar/postgresql/9.3.3/homebrew.mxcl.postgresql.plist ~/Library/LaunchAgents/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setup DB from SQL file:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;### Setup DB
lunchy start postgres
created $DBNAME
psql -d $DBNAME -f &#39;/path/to/file.sql&#39;
lunchy stop postgres
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starting and Stopping PostgreSQL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;lunchy start postgres
lunchy stop postgres
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;may run into trouble with local socket… try this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rm /usr/local/var/postgres/postmaster.pid
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connecting with R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;# make sure lunch start postgres in terminal first)
require(dplyr)
db &amp;lt;- src_postgres(dbname=$DBNAME)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://altons.github.io/r/2015/01/22/an-easy-way-of-installing-rpostgresql-on-mac/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; and thought I should toss out what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking Control</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2015/01/taking-control</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2015/01/taking-control</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;severing-my-daemon&#34;&gt;Severing My Daemon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in high school, I piggy-backed on a friend&amp;rsquo;s website to host a page for my band. We could post pictures, show locations and dates, lyrics, and pretend like we produced music people cared about. It was mostly a fun way for me to play with the web and something to show folks when I said I played guitar and sang in a band. One day, my friend canceled his hosting. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t using his site for anything and he forgot that I had been using the site. I was 18, I never thought about backups, and I had long deleted all those pesky photos taking up space on my memory cards and small local hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years of photos from some of the best experiences of my life are gone. No one had copies. Everyone was using the site. In the decade since, no set of pictures has ever been as valuable as the ones I lost that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-controls-the-past&#34;&gt;Who controls the past&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, this loss has had a profound effect on how I think about both my data and the permanence of the internet. Today, I have a deep system of backups for any digital data I produce, and I am far more likely to err on keeping data than discarding it. Things still sometimes go missing. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:stage&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:stage&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the more lasting impact is my desire to maintain some control over all of my data. I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fastmail.fm/?STKI=11467093&#34;&gt;Fastmail&lt;/a&gt; for my email, even after over 10 years of GMail use. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:early&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:early&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I like knowing that I am storing some of my most important data in a standard way that easily syncs locally and backs up. I like that I pay directly for such an important service so that all of the incentive for my email provider is around making email work better for me. I am the customer. I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.getsync.com&#34;&gt;Bittorrent Sync&lt;/a&gt; for a good chunk of my data. I want redundancy across multiple machines and syncing, but I don&amp;rsquo;t want all of my work and all of my data to depend on being on a third party server like it is with Dropbox. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:db&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:db&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I also use a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.esn.fm/sponsors/&#34;&gt;Transporter&lt;/a&gt; so that some of my files are stored on a local hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;raison-d-être&#34;&gt;Raison D&amp;rsquo;être&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this blog exist? I have played with &lt;a href=&#34;http://tumblr.jsonbecker.com&#34;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; in the past and I like its social and discovery tools, but I do not like the idea of pouring my thoughts into someone else&amp;rsquo;s service with no guarantee of easy or clean exit. I tried using Wordpress on a self-hosted blog for a while, but I took one look at the way my blog posts were being stored in the Wordpress database and kind of freaked out. All those convenient plugins and short codes were transforming the way my actual text was stored in hard to recover way. Plus, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really understand how my data was stored well enough to be comfortable I had solid back ups. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to lose my writing like I lost those pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog exists, built on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.getpelican.com&#34;&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, because I needed to a place to write my thoughts in plain text that was as easy to back up as it was to share with the world. I don&amp;rsquo;t write often, and I feel I rarely write the &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; of my thoughts, but if I am going to take the time to put something out in the world I want to be damn sure that I control it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bag-end&#34;&gt;Bag End&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently began a journey that I thought was about simplifying tools. I began using &lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt; a lot more for text editing, including writing prose like this post. But I quickly found that my grasping for new ways to do work was less about simplifying and more about better control. I want to be able to work well, with little interruption, on just about any computer. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to use anything that&amp;rsquo;s overly expensive or available only on one platform if I can avoid it. I want to strip away dependencies as much as possible. And while much of what I already use is free software, I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like I was in &lt;em&gt;control&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; has been an amazing change for how I do all my work since about 2011. Github is a major part of my daily work and has saved me a bunch of money by allowing me to host this site for free. But I started getting frustrated with limitations of not having an actual server and not really having access to the power and control that a real server provides. So I recently moved this site off of Github and on to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digitalocean.com/?refcode=7377c1fcbe67&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; droplet. This is my first experiment with running a Linux VPS. Despite using desktop Linux for four years full time, I have never administered a server. It feels like a skill I should have and I really like the control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;quentin-s-land&#34;&gt;Quentin&amp;rsquo;s Land&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This whole blog is about having a place I control where I can write things. I am getting better at the control part, but I really need to work on the writing things part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I hope to do in the next few months. I am going to choose (or write) a new theme for the site that&amp;rsquo;s responsive and has a bit more detail. I am probably going to write a little bit about the cool, simple things I learned about &lt;code&gt;nginx&lt;/code&gt; and how moving to my own server is helping me run this page (and other experiments) with a lot more flexibility. I am also going to try and shift some of my writing from tweetstorms to short blog posts. If I am truly trying to control my writing, I need to do a better job of thinking out loud in this space versus treating them as disposable and packing them on to Twitter. I will also be sharing more code snippets and ideas and less thoughts on policy and local (Rhode Island) politics. The code/statistics/data stuff feels easier to write and has always gotten more views and comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the plan for 2015. Time to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:stage&#34;&gt;I recently found some rare music missing that I had to retrieve through some heroic efforts that included [Archive.org]() and stalking someone from an online forum that no longer exists (successfully).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:stage&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:early&#34;&gt;I was a very early adopter of Gmail.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:early&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:db&#34;&gt;I still use Dropbox. I&amp;rsquo;m not an animal. But I like having an alternative.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:db&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazon Creating A Services Marketplace Online</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/amazon-creating-a-services-marketplace-online</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/amazon-creating-a-services-marketplace-online</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a very interesting way to take advantage of a number of existing Amazon technologies&amp;ndash;primarily their payment processing and review system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Services are an increasingly important part of the economy and is less subject to commoditization. This is Amazon dipping into a massive growth area by commoditizing discovery and payment. It also offloads some of the risk from both sides of the transaction. It&amp;rsquo;s very bold, possibly brilliant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have tried to find a reliable carpenter, electrician, plumber, house cleaning service, etc lately, it should be obvious the value that Amazon can provide. Even as a subscriber to Angie&amp;rsquo;s List, which has been invaluable, finding reliable, affordable, and quality services is still a frustrating experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is why technology companies get huge valuations. It is hard to anticipate just how technologies to become the first online booksellers will lead to a massive number of accounts with credit cards and a strongly trusted brand. It is hard to anticipate how book reviews and powerful search andfiltering become the way you find people to come into your home and fix a toilet. But truly, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to anticipate the limits of a company with massive reach into people&amp;rsquo;s wallets that scales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power Of Sound</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/the-power-of-sound</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/the-power-of-sound</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been said a thousand times before, but I feel the need to say it again. So much of what Star Wars got right was creating a fully realized, fascinating world. As much as stunning visual effects that have largely stood the test of time were a part of that story, it was how Star Wars &lt;em&gt;sounded&lt;/em&gt; that is most remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch that trailer. It has moments that &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; an awful lot like Star Wars&amp;ndash; vast dunes in the middle of the desert, the Millenium Falcon speeding along, flipping at odd angles emphasizing its unique flat structure. But it also has a lot of elemetns that are decidedly modern and not Star Wars like. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:shakes&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:shakes&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I think what&amp;rsquo;s most remarkable is I can close my eyes and just listen. Immediately I can &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; Star Wars. The sounds of Star Wars are not just iconic, they are deeply embedded in my psyche and embued with profound meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first had the opportunity to see Star Wars on the big screen it was during the release of the &amp;ldquo;Special Editions&amp;rdquo;. There is nothing like hearing Star Wars in a theater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:shakes&#34;&gt;Shakey-cam is the primary culprit.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:shakes&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School Funding Reform, Hard Work and Fraught with Potential</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/school-funding-reform-hard-work-and-fraught-with-potential</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/school-funding-reform-hard-work-and-fraught-with-potential</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the primacy of equity as a goal in school finance system design, the formulas disproportionately benefit less wealthy districts and those with high concentrations of needier students.
&amp;hellip;
because of the universal impact on communities, school finance legislation requires broad political buy-in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is worth contrasting the political realities of constructing school finance law with the need and justification for state funding of education in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state is the in the business of funding schools for redistributive purposes. If that wasn&amp;rsquo;t required, there&amp;rsquo;s little reason to not trade an inefficient pass through of sales and income tax dollars through to communities that could have lower sales and income taxes (or state sales and income taxes) replaced with local sales, income, property taxes , and fees. We come together as states to solve problems that extend beyond parochial boundaries, and our political unions exist to tackle problems we&amp;rsquo;re not better off tackling alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are limits to redistributive policy. Support for the needs of other communities might wane, leading to challenging and reducing the rights of children with new law or legal battles, serious political consequences for supporters of redistirbution, and decreased in economic activity (in education, property value). These are real pressures that need to be combatted both by convincing voters and through policy success &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:lack&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:lack&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. There are also considerations around the ethics of &amp;ldquo;bailing out&amp;rdquo; communities that made costly mistakes like constructing too many buildings or offering far too generous rights to staff in contracts that they cannot afford to maintain. We struggle as policy experts to not create the opportunity for moral hazards as we push to support children who need our help today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policy experts and legal experts cannot excuse the needs of children today, nor can they fail to face the limits of support for redistribution or incentivizing bad adult behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:lack&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t doubt that support for redistributive policy goes south when it appears that our efforts to combat poverty and provide equal opportunities appear to fail, over and over again, and in many cases may actually make things worse.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:lack&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do we attract the best teachers to struggling schools?</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/how-do-we-attract-the-best-teachers-to-struggling-schools</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/how-do-we-attract-the-best-teachers-to-struggling-schools</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are some basic facts about the teacher labor market that are &lt;em&gt;inconvenient&lt;/em&gt; for many folks working to improve education. I am going to go through a few premises that I think should be broadly accepted and several lemma and contentions that I hope clarifies my own view on education resources and human capital management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching in low performing schools is challenging.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I am looking for a job, all else being equal, I will generally not choose the more challenging one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some may object to the idea that teachers would not accept a position that offers a greater opportunity to make a difference, for example, teaching at an inner city school, over one that was less likely to have an impact, like teaching in a posh, suburban neighborhood. It is certainly true that some teachers, if not most teachers place value on making a greater impact. However, the question is how great is that preference? How much less compensation (not just wage) would the median teacher be willing to take to work in a more challenging environment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I contend that it is atypical for teachers to accept lower compensation for a more challenging job. I would further suggest that even if there were a sufficient number of teachers to staff all urban schools with those that would accept lower compensation for a position in those schools, the gap in compensation that they would accept is low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are large gaps in non-pecuniary compensation between high performing school and low performing schools that is difficult to overcome.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us supposed that it&amp;rsquo;s true there are large parts of the teacher workforce that would accept lower compensation (wage and non-wage) to teach in urban schools. There are real benefits to taking on a role where the potential for impact is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we can consider this benefit as part of the &lt;em&gt;hedonic wages&lt;/em&gt; supplied by a teaching role. Other forms of non-monetary compensation that teachers may experience include: a comfortable physical work environment with sufficient space, lighting, and climate control; sufficient supplies to teach effectively; support and acceptance of their students, their families, and the broader school communities; a safe work environment; job security; alignment to a strong, unified school culture; and strong self-efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these features &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be easily replicated in many low performing schools. It is possible to have better quality physical schools and sufficient funding for supplies. Other features can be replicated, but not nearly as easily. Low performing schools where students have complex challenges inside and outside of the classroom are not environments where everyone has a strong sense of self-efficacy. Even the initial sense that making a difference is within reach erodes for many after facing a challenging environment day after day, year after year. A safe environment and a strong school culture are well within reach, but hardly easy and hardly universal. These things should be universal. They require funding, leadership, and broadly successful organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is not that all high performing schools always have these features and no low performing schools can or do have these features. What is important is that many of these features are less often found in low performing, particularly urban schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I contend that the typical gap in non-pecuniary compensation between high and low performing schools is large enough to wipe out any negative compensating wage differential that may exist due to a desire for greater impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The primary mechanism to get &amp;ldquo;more&amp;rdquo; education is increasing the quality or quantity of teaching.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us take the leap of suggesting that teaching is a key part of the production of education. If we want to improve educational equity and address the needs of low performing schools, we need some combination of more and higher quality teaching. This is a key driver of policies like extended learning time (more), smaller class sizes (more), professional development (better), and teacher evaluation and support systems (better). It is what is behind improving teacher preparation programs (better), alternative certification (better), and progressive support programs like RTI (more and better).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NaNo(Blo)WriMo</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/nanoblowrimo</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2014/11/nanoblowrimo</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;November marks the start of National Novel Writing Month (NaNoWriMo). The quick version is folks band together and support each other to write 50,000 words in November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to write a novel one day. I am not sure I could do it well, but I am pretty sure I could hit 50,000-80,000 words if I dedicated time to tell a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have a story to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this year, I have decided to not feel guilty about skipping out on another NaNoWriMo (&lt;em&gt;always the reader, never the author&lt;/em&gt;), and instead I am modifying it to meet my needs. With no story to tell and no experience tackling a single project the size of a novel, I am going to tackle a smaller problem&amp;ndash; this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of 50,000 words in 30 days, I am going to try and write 1000 words a day for the next four weeks. I will not hold myself to a topic. I will not even hold myself to non-fiction. I will not hold myself to a number of posts or the size of the posts I write. I will not even hold myself to true daily count, instead reviewing where I stand at the end of each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hoping that the practice of simply writing will grease my knuckles and start the avalanche that leads to writing more. A small confession&amp;ndash; I write two or three blog posts every week that never leave my drafts. I find myself unable to hit publish because the ideas tend to be far larger or far smaller than I anticipate when I set out to write and share my frustrations. I also get nervous, particularly when writing about things I do professionally, about not writing the perfect post that&amp;rsquo;s clear, heavily researched, and expresses my views definitively and completely. This month, I say goodbye to that anxiety and start simply hitting publish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will leave you with several warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things might get topically wacky. I might suddenly become a food blogger, or write about more personal issues, or write a short story and suddenly whiplash to talking about programming, education policy, or the upcoming election. If high volume, random topics aren&amp;rsquo;t your thing, you should probably unsubscribe from my RSS feed and check back in a month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I might write terrible arguments that are poorly supported and don&amp;rsquo;t reflect my views. This month, I will not accept my most common excuses for not publishing, which boil down to fear people will hold me to the views I express in my first-draft thinking. I am going to make mistakes this month in public and print the dialog I am having with myself. The voices I allow room to speak as I struggle with values, beliefs, and opinions may be shock and offend. This month, this blog is my internal dialog. Please read it as a struggle, however definitive the tone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am often disappointed that the only things I publish are smaller ideas written hastily with poor editing. Again, this month I embrace the reality that almost everything I write that ends up published is the result of 20 minutes of furious typing with no looking back, rather than trying to be a strong writer with a strong view point and strong support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that the end of this month I will have written at least a couple of pieces I feel proud of, and hopefully, I will have a little less fear of hitting publish in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Growing Up in the Internet Hate Machine</title>
      <link>http://www.json.blog/2014/10/growing-up-in-the-internet-hate-machine</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.json.blog/2014/10/growing-up-in-the-internet-hate-machine</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A terrible thing is happening this year. Women all across the internet are finding themselves the target of violence, simply for existing. Women are being harassed for talking about video games, women are being harassed for talking about the technology industry, women are being harassed for talking, women are being harassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A terrible thing is happening. Women are finding themselves the target of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A terrible thing has always happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember being a 16 year old posting frequently on internet forums. One in particular focused on guitar equipment. I loved playing in a band, and I loved the technology of making guitar sounds. Many people on the forum were between 16 and 24, although it was frequented by quite a few &amp;ldquo;adults&amp;rdquo; in their 30s, 40s, and 50s. It was a wonderful opportunity to interact as an adult, with adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week members created a new thread where they posted hundreds of photos of women. Most of them were professional photographs taken at various night clubs as patrons entered. Some were magazine clippings or fashion modeling. I remember taking part, both in gazing and supplying the occasional photograph from the internet. We were far from the early days of the world wide web, this being around 2003, but this was also before social media matured and online identity was well understood by the general public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thread became controversial. A change from private to corporate ownership of this forum led to increased moderation, and the weekly post with photos of women was one of the targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the debates about the appropriateness of the content and its place within our online community, I took the side of those who wanted the post to remain alive. I was not its most ardent supporter, nor was I moved to some of the extremes in language and entitlement that typically surround these conversations. However, my views were clear and easy. These were public photographs, largely taken with permission (often for compensation). And, of course, none of the pictures were &lt;em&gt;pornographic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appropriateness for me at 16 was defined by &lt;em&gt;pornography&lt;/em&gt;. I did not understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents did not raise me to be misogynist. One of the most influential moments in my life came on a car ride to the dentist. I was also around 16 or 17. I think it was on my way to get my wisdom teeth removed. I had been dating the same girl for a while, and it was time for my father to give me &lt;em&gt;the talk&lt;/em&gt;. All he said to me was, &amp;ldquo;Women deserve your respect.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were in college, and my friends and I were all &lt;em&gt;internet natives&lt;/em&gt;. We had used the web for over ten years. We grew up in AOL chatrooms and forums. The backwaters of the internet at this time shifted from Something Awful to 4Chan. This was the height of some of the most prolific and hilarious memes: lolcats, &lt;a href=&#34;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/xzibit-yo-dawg&#34;&gt;Xzibit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/advice-dog&#34;&gt;advice dogs&lt;/a&gt; (a favorite was &lt;a href=&#34;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/foul-bachelor-frog&#34;&gt;bachelor frog&lt;/a&gt;, which seemed to understand our worst impulses expressed in only modest exaggeration).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not uncommon to see names, phone numbers, and addresses that 4chan was supposed to harass because someone said so. Various subcultures seemed to be alternatively mocked and harassed endlessly in the very place that had first embraced, supported, and connected people under the guise of radical anonymity. The most famous of the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/rules-of-the-internet&#34;&gt;Rules of the Internet&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; was Rule 34 &amp;ndash; if you can think of it, there is a porn of it&amp;ndash; and its follow up, Rule 35 &amp;ndash; if you can not find porn of it, you should make it. 4chan seemed determined to make this a reality. But really the most troublesome thing was the attitude toward women. Nothing was as unacceptable to 4chan as suggesting that women are anything but objects for male gaze. In a place sometimes filled with radically liberal (if more left-libertarian than left-progressive) politics that would spawn groups like &lt;a href=&#34;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/subcultures/anonymous&#34;&gt;Anonymous&lt;/a&gt;, nothing brought out as much criticism as suggesting our culture has a problem with women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response was largely to fade from this part of the internet. I had only reached the point of being &lt;em&gt;uncomfortable&lt;/em&gt; with this behavior. It would take more time for me to understand. It still felt like this was a problem of ignorant people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am rarely jealous of intelligence. I am rarely jealous of wealth. I am rarely jealous of experiences. What I am most often jealous of is what seems to me to be a preternatural maturity of others, particularly around issues of ethics and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fully grappling with privilege is not something that happens over a moment, it is a sensitivity to be developed over a lifetime. We are confronted with media that builds and reinforces a culture that is fundamentally intolerant and conservative. There are countless microaggressions that are modeled everywhere for our acceptance as normal. It has taken me a decade of maturation, hard conversations, and self-examination to only begin to grow from fully complicit and participating in objectification of women to what I would now consider to be the most basic level of human decency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet has gone from enabling my own aggression toward women to exposing me to a level of misogyny and violence that deeply disturbs and disgusts me, shattering any notion that my past offenses were harmless or victimless. The ugly underside of our culture is constantly on display, making it all the more obvious how what felt like isolated events on the &amp;ldquo;ok&amp;rdquo; side of the line were actaully creating a space that supported and nurtured the worst compulsions of men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt; &lt;/hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often think about my own journey when I see disgusting behavior on the internet. I wonder whether I am facing a deeply, ugly person or myself at 16. I try to parse the difference between naïvety, ignorance, and hate and to understand if they require a unique response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly, I struggle with what would happen if Jason Today spoke to Jason 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jason 16 could not skip over a decade of growth simply for having met Jason Today. It took me conversations with various folks playing the role of Jason Today over and over again, year after year. I wish I believed there was another way to reach the Jason 16s out there. I wish I knew how to help them become preternaturally aware of their actions. All I know how to do is try to be compassionate to those who hate while firmly correcting, try to meet the heightened expectations I place on myself, try to apologize when I need to, and try to support those that seem more equipped to push the conversation forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along this path, I never lept to agreement so much as paused. Each time I heard a convincing point, I paused and considered. Growth came in a series of all too brief pauses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pauses are often private and quiet, its discoveries never on direct display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If pauses are the best anyone can expect, then working to change our culture of violence toward women will rarely feel like much more than shouting at the void.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>