<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Service Home Improvement on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/service-home-improvement/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Service Home Improvement on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jsonbecker.com/tags/service-home-improvement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazon Creating A Services Marketplace Online</title>
      <link>http://www.jsonbecker.com/post/amazon-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jsonbecker.com/post/amazon-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a very interesting way to take advantage of a number of existing Amazon technologies&amp;ndash;primarily their payment processing and review system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Services are an increasingly important part of the economy and is less subject to commoditization. This is Amazon dipping into a massive growth area by commoditizing discovery and payment. It also offloads some of the risk from both sides of the transaction. It&amp;rsquo;s very bold, possibly brilliant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have tried to find a reliable carpenter, electrician, plumber, house cleaning service, etc lately, it should be obvious the value that Amazon can provide. Even as a subscriber to Angie&amp;rsquo;s List, which has been invaluable, finding reliable, affordable, and quality services is still a frustrating experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is why technology companies get huge valuations. It is hard to anticipate just how technologies to become the first online booksellers will lead to a massive number of accounts with credit cards and a strongly trusted brand. It is hard to anticipate how book reviews and powerful search andfiltering become the way you find people to come into your home and fix a toilet. But truly, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to anticipate the limits of a company with massive reach into people&amp;rsquo;s wallets that scales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>