<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Education Pvd Ppsd Bilingual Ell on JSONBecker</title>
    <link>/tags/education-pvd-ppsd-bilingual-ell/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Education Pvd Ppsd Bilingual Ell on JSONBecker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/education-pvd-ppsd-bilingual-ell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bilingual Education at Providence Public Schools</title>
      <link>/2013/11/bilingual-education-at-providence-public-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/bilingual-education-at-providence-public-schools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are trying to work towards late-exit ELL programs so (students) can learn the concepts in (their) native language,” Lusi said. Administrative goals have recently shifted to a focus on proficiency in both languages because bilingual education is preferred, she added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But instituting district-wide bilingual education would require funding to hire teachers certified in both languages and to buy dual-language materials, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure this is new. I am surprised there has not been a stronger effort to pass a legislative package in Rhode Island that provides both the policy framework and funding necessary to achieve universal bilinguage education for English language learners in RI schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the great advantages of transitioning to common standards&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:CCSS&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:CCSS&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is there should be greater availability of curricular materials in languages other than English. I suspect most of what is needed for bilingual education is start up money for materials, curriculum supports and developments, and assessment materials. There are a few policy things that need to be in place, possibly around state exams, but also rules around flexible teacher assignment, hiring, and dismissal staffing needs dramatically change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone should be putting this package together. I suspect there would be broad support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:CCSS&#34;&gt;Note, this is not necessarily a feature of the Common Core State Standards, just having standards in common with many other states.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:CCSS&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
